DR. IOANA-ELENA OANA

Research Fellow European University Institute

■ Badia Fiesolana - BF260, Via dei Roccettini 9, 50014, Fiesole, Italy

☆ ioana.oana@eui.eu ◇ ★ https://nenaoana.github.io

I am a Research Fellow at the European University Institute within the framework of the SOLID project led by Prof. Hanspeter Kriesi. My current work focuses on collective mobilization, public opinion, and party competition dynamics for the study of the multiple crises that have hit the EU since 2008. My broader research interests include political behavior, political participation and mobilization, political representation, and public opinion formation. Beyond my substantive interests, a lot of my work also focuses on research methodology and R software development with a pluralist outlook. I work with text as data solutions for semi-automated protest event analysis, surveys and survey experiments, and I develop analytic protools and software for qualitative comparative analysis.

ACADEMIC POSITIONS

Research Fellow 06/2019 - present

SOLID ERC Project (PI: Prof. Hanspeter Kriesi) European University Institute, Florence, Italy

Research Fellow 02/2019 - 06/2019

POLCON ERC Project (PI: Prof. Hanspeter Kriesi) European University Institute, Florence, Italy

EDUCATION

PhD in Comparative Politics

09/2013 - 04/2019

Central European University, Budapest (Supervisor: Prof. Zsolt Enyedi)

Thesis: Collective Mobilization and Dynamic Representation: From Citizens to Policy and Back Again

MA in Political Science (Distinction)

09/2011 - 09/2013

Specialization: Social Science Methodology

Central European University, Budapest (Supervisor: Prof. Levente Littvay)

Thesis: When does information matter? Complexity, Cognitive Heuristics and Democratic Competence

BA in Political Science (Valedictorian, GPA: 4.00)

09/2008 - 06/2011

Department of Political Science, SNSPA, Bucharest

BA in Communication and Public Relations (Thesis not submitted)

09/2008 - 06/2011

Department of Communication and Public Relations, SNSPA, Bucharest

LIST OF PUBLICATIONS

Books (peer-reviewed)

Ioana-Elena Oana, Carsten Q. Schneider, and Eva Thomann. 2021. "Qualitative Comparative Analysis using R: A Beginner's Guide." Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.

Peer-reviewed Articles

Ioana-Elena Oana, Alessandro Pellegata, and Chendi Wang. 2021. "A cure worse than the disease? Exploring the health-economy trade-off during COVID-19." West European Politics 44(5-6): 1232-1257.

Ioana-Elena Oana and Carsten Q. Schneider. 2021. "A Robustness Test Protocol for Applied QCA: Theory and R Software Application." Sociological Methods & Research. https://doi.org/10.1177/00491241211036158.

Endre Borbath, Sophia Hunger, Swen Hutter and **Ioana-Elena Oana**. 2021. "Civic and Political Engagement during the Multifaceted COVID-19 Crisis". Swiss Political Science Review 27: 311-324.

Hanspeter Kriesi, Argyrios Altiparmakis, Abel Bojar and **Ioana-Elena Oana**. 2021. "Debordering and re-bordering in the refugee crisis: a case of 'defensive integration'". Journal of European Public Policy 28(3): 331-349.

Ioana-Elena Oana. 2019. "Party and protest participation patterns among students in new and old democracies." Partecipazione e Conflitto 12(1): 71-111.

Maarten and Bezouw, Anastasia Garyfallou, **Ioana-Elena Oana**, Sebastien Rojon. 2019. "A methodology for cross-national comparative focus group research: illustrations from discussions about political protest." Quality & Quantity 53(6): 2719-2739.

Ioana-Elena Oana and Carsten Schneider. 2018. "SetMethods: an Add-on Package for Advanced QCA." The R Journal 10(1): 507-533.

Marcel Verhoeven and **Ioana-Elena Oana**. 2017. "Necessary and Sufficient Conditions for Audience Success of Media Product Brands: A field report on a two-step fsQCA with 10 conditions and 255 cases." COMPASSS WP Series 89.

Chapters in Edited Volumes & Other Publications

Ioana-Elena Oana and Hanspeter Kriesi. 2021. Asylum Policy Preferences Among the European Publics: Confict Configurations at the Transnational and Domestic Level." Robert Schuman Centre for Advanced Studies Research Paper No. RSC 93.

Ioana-Elena Oana. 2019. "Reinvigorating Romania's Civil Society: Talking About Politics and Corruption in Romania.", In When Citizens Talk About Politics. Eds. Clare Saunders and Bert Klandermans. Routledge.

Maarten and Bezouw, Anastasia Garyfallou, **Ioana-Elena Oana**, Sebastien Rojon, Clare Saunders. 2019. "Methodological appendix - Studying political talk using cross-national focus groups." In When Citizens Talk About Politics. Eds. Clare Saunders and Bert Klandermans. Routledge.

Ioana-Elena Oana. 2014. "The economy of dictatorship and democracy." In Economic and Evolutionary Approaches in Social Sciences. Ed. Mihai Ungureanu, Wolters Kluver, pp. 67-86.

Software Packages

Ioana-Elena Oana, Juraj Medzihorsky, Mario Quaranta, Carsten Q. Schneider. 2018. SetMethods: Functions for Set-Theoretic Multi-Method Research and Advanced QCA. R package (45,000 CRAN downloads).

Ioana-Elena Oana. 2020. MDScosa: Functions for Multidimensional Scaling of Election Campaign Data. R package .

Engagement & Outreach Publications

Ioana-Elena Oana. 2021. "Covid-19: spur or restraint to citizen engagement?." EUIdeas Blog post.

Hanspeter Kriesi and **Ioana-Elena Oana**. 2021. "Transnational and domestic conflicts in asylum policies: preferences among the European publics." Migration Policy Center Blog post.

Ioana-Elena Oana and Hanspeter Kriesi. 2020. "Report on Coronavirus Survey in Italy: First Two Waves." EUI European Governance and Politics Programme. Online Research Report

Ioana-Elena Oana and Hanspeter Kriesi. 2020. "Report on Coronavirus Survey in Italy: Comparison of First Three Waves." EUI European Governance and Politics Programme. Online Research Report

Thomann, Eva, **Ioana-Elena Oana**, and Stefan Wittwer. 2018. "Performing fuzzy and crisp set QCA with R: A user-oriented beginner's guide."

Work in Progress

Book manuscripts

Hanspeter Kriesi, Argyrios Altiparmakis, Abel Bojar, and **Ioana-Elena Oana**. "Coming to terms with the refugee crisis in the EU." Manuscript finalized for submission at Cambridge University Press.

Ioana-Elena Oana. "Collective Mobilization and Dynamic Representation: From Citizens to Policy and Back Again." Manuscript in progress (based on PhD thesis monograph).

Special Issues

Ioana-Elena Oana, Stefano Ronchi, and Zbigniew Truchlewski. "EU polity resilience in times of COVID? Solidarity, legitimacy, and polity maintenance." Special Issue accepted at Journal of European Integration.

Papers in peer review

Ioana-Elena Oana, Abel Bojar, and Chendi Wang. The COVID-19 lockdown paradox: support for democracy in times of democratic restrictions.

Ioana-Elena Oana and Abel Bojar. Populism, dissatisfaction, and COVID-19 related conspiracy beliefs across Europe.

Hanspeter Kriesi and **Ioana-Elena Oana**. Protest in unlikely times: dynamics of collective mobilization in the COVID-19 crisis in Europe.

Chendi Wang, Abel Bojar, **Ioana-Elena Oana**, and Zbigniew Truchlewski. Mass Sentiment towards the EU during COVID's First Wave: A Longitudinal Analysis of Social Media Data.

Abel Bojar, Anna Kyriazi, Zbigniew Truchlewski, and **Ioana-Elena Oana**. Policy Process Analysis: an introduction to a novel method.

Chapters in progress

Ioana-Elena Oana. Qualitative Comparative Analysis. In Oxford Handbook: Doing Good Qualitative Research. Eds. Jennifer Cyr and Sara Wallace Goodman. Oxford University Press.

Ioana-Elena Oana and Carsten Q. Schneider. Qualitative Comparative Analysis. In Elgar Concise Encyclopedia of Research Methods in the Social Sciences. Edward Elgal Publishing.

Papers in progress

Ioana-Elena Oana. Policy output legitimacy in the refugee crisis: A survey experiment on the consequences of asylum policy for EU support in Europe.

Ioana-Elena Oana and Zbigniew Truchlewski. Transnational and domestic solidarity in the COVID-19 crisis: evidence from a survey experiment in eight European countries.

Ioana-Elena Oana. The political bases and consequences of COVID-19 vaccine hesitancy.

Ioana-Elena Oana. Explaining individual preferences for asylum and migration policy.

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE PRIOR TO CURRENT POSITION

POLPART ADVANCED ERC (PI: Prof. Bert Klandermans)

08/2014-11/2018

Research Affiliate

- gathering and analyzing survey, experimental, and focus group data on party and protest participation in Europe;

POLCON ADVANCED ERC (PI: Prof. Hanspeter Kriesi)

04/2017-09/2017

Coder

- coding contentious political events in Romania;

"Experimental Political Behavior" (CEU Research Support Scheme)

01/2013-07/2013

Scheme Beneficiary

(awarded to Prof. Levente Littvay, CEU, Budapest)

- designing and conducting a lab experiment on voting behavior;

Pilot Study "The Post-Socialist Welfare States" (PI: Prof. Julia Szalai) 03/2012-07/2012 Research Assistant

- collecting and analyzing interview data with public servants in Romania;

RESEARCH VISITS

European University Institute, Florence, Italy

01/2017 - 05/2017

Department of Political and Social Sciences (Host Supervisor: Prof. Hanspeter Kriesi)

VU University, Amsterdam, Netherlands

01/2015 - 07/2015

Department of Sociology (Host Supervisor: Prof. Bert Klandermans)

University of Padua, Padua, Italy

09/2009 - 02/2010

Department of Political Science

GRANTS, AWARDS & FUNDING

Marie Skłodowska-Curie Individual Fellowship (€212,933, not accepted due to current position) 02/2019

Full CEU Doctoral Fellowship (Tuition: €30,000; Stipend: €25,500)

09/2013-02/2019

ECPR Dirk-Berg Schlosser Award for outstanding pedagogical skills (€500)

08/2018

Marie Skłodowska-Curie Individual Fellowship Seal of Excellence

04/2018

National Science Foundation and Maxwell School Grant for attending IQMR, Maxwell School, Syracuse University, NY, USA (Amount: €300 + accommodation) 06/2017

CEU Summer School Grant for attending the IQMR, Maxwell School, Syracuse University, NY, USA (Amount: €694)

06/2017

CEU Conference and Travel Grant for the ECPR Joint Sessions of Workshops, Nottingham (Amount: €570)

CEU Doctoral Research Support Grant for a research stay at EUI, Florence (Amount: €4,000) 05/2016

CEU Conference Grant for the ECPR General Conference, Prague (Amount: €448) 06/2016 CEU Departmental Award for Excellence in Master Studies 02/2012 CEU Full Fellowship for Master Students (Tuition: €24,000; Stipend: €6,000 + accommodation) 09/2011-06/2013 Valedictorian Award, Department of Political Science, SNSPA, Bucharest 06/2011 "Olympic Merit" Scholarship from the Romanian Government (Amount: €3,500) 09/2008-06/2011 Merit Scholarship from the Department of Political Science, SNSPA, Bucharest (Amount: €2,500) 09/2008-06/2011 TEACHING EXPERIENCE Graduate & PhD Level courses & workshops Institute for Qualitative & Multi-Method Research, Syracuse University, USA 2021 Qualitative Comparative Analysis with R IPSA-FLACSO Mexico Summer School - Virtual Qualitative Comparative Analysis with R **ECPR Virtual Methods School** Qualitative Comparative Analysis with R ECPR Virtual Methods School Advanced Qualitative Comparative Analysis ECPR Virtual Methods School 2020 Qualitative Comparative Analysis with R ECPR Virtual Methods School Advanced Qualitative Comparative Analysis ECPR Summer School in Methods and Techniques 2019 Introduction to Case-Based Research and Set-Theoretic Thinking ECPR Summer School in Methods and Techniques Qualitative Comparative Analysis and Fuzzy-Sets ECPR Winter School in Methods and Techniquesy Seasoned Scholar Workshops: Quantitative and Qualitative Methods - Selected Topics Antwerp Management School, Belgium Intermediate QCA University of Helsinki, Finland R for QCA West University, Romania 2018 Introduction to QCA in R Lund University, Sweden Introduction to QCA in R

University of Exeter Q-Step Centre, UK Introduction to Qualitative Comparative Analysis

ECPR Summer School in Methods and Techniques

Seasoned Scholar Workshops: Qualitative and Multi-Method Research - Selected Topics

European University Institute, Italy

Qualitative Comparative Analysis (QCA) with R

ECPR Summer School in Methods and Techniques

2013-2017

Teaching Assistant for Qualitative Comparative Analysis and Fuzzy-Sets

- 5 times
- included teaching Introduction to R and teaching lab seminars in R $\it Teaching \ Assistant for \ Advanced \ Qualitative \ Comparative \ Analysis$
- 4 times
- included teaching Introduction to R and teaching lab seminars in R

METHODS TRAINING

Institute for Qualitative & Multi-Method Research, Maxwell School, Syracuse, USA

Workshops Attended: Automated Text-Analysis; Multi-method research; Natural experiments; Causal inference from causal models; QCA; 06/2017

ECPR Winter School in Methods and Techniques, Bamberg

Workshop Attended: Multi-level modeling

03/2016

Central European University, Budapest

<u>Methods classes attended:</u> Quantitative Methods: Analyzing Countries, Research Methods and Design, Multivariate Statistics, Survey Methodology, Qualitative Research Methods, Set-Theoretic Methods for the Social Sciences, Network Science, Experimental Methods, Mathematical Statistics, Missing Data Problems in Statistical Inference;

2011-2015

SERVICE TO THE PROFESSION

Reviewer for: American Political Science Review, West European Politics, Sociological Methods & Research, Regulation & Governance, Policy Studies Journal, Quality & Quantity, Social Movement Studies, Compasss Working Paper Series, PLOS ONE

SELECTED CONFERENCE PAPERS & GUEST LECTURES

ECPR Conference of the Standing Group on European Union

06/2021

Populism, Dissatisfaction, and COVID-19 related Conspiracy Beliefs across Europe

KU Leuven, Master program in European policies and politics

02/2021

Guest Lecture in Comparative Analysis for Public Policy

Expert Workshop on QCA, Antwerp Management School, Belgium

05/2019

Case Orientation and Parameters of Fit Orientation. A Proposal for Systematized Robustness Tests in QCA using R

West University of Timisoara, Romania

11/2018

Guest Lecture on Party and Protest Participation Patterns among Students in New and Old Democracies

International QCA Expert Workshop, ETH Zurich, Switzerland

11/2018

Fit-oriented and Case-oriented Robustness in QCA

Exeter Doctoral Conference, University of Exeter, UK

03/2018

How Policy Change affects Alternative Participation - A Vignette Experiment

Annual Doctoral Conference, Central European University, Budapest, Hungary 03/2018 The Participation Consequences of Policy Change – A Vignette Experiment

ECPR Joint Sessions of Workshops, Nottingham, UK

04/2017

The Policy Consequences of Alternative Participation: Civil Society Events and Governmental Attention to Issues

Annual Doctoral Conference, Central European University, Budapest, Hungary

04/2017

The Consequences of Alternative Participation: Civil Society Events and Public Expenditure

POLPART ADVANCED ERC Project Midterm Conference, Budapest, Hungary 09/2016 Pseudo-reality and self-defeating rationalizations: Mental frames of Political Participation in Romania and Hungary

ECPR General Conference, Prague, Czech Republic

09/2016

Income Inequality and Policy Responsiveness Perceptions: A Genetic Matching Approach

ECPR General Conference, Prague, Czech Republic

09/2016

Civil Society Events, Media, and Environmental Protection Expenditure in Europe

Annual Doctoral Conference, Central European University, Budapest, Hungary 04/2016 Income Inequality and Policy Responsiveness Perceptions: A Genetic Matching Approach

Annual Doctoral Conference, Central European University, Budapest, Hungary 04/2015 Movements' Impact, Media, and Policy Outputs: A Fuzzy-Set Analysis of Environmental Events' Effects on Environmental Protection Expenditure in Italy

International Association for Media and Communication Research Annual Conference, Dublin, Ireland 06/2013

Internet as a catalyzer for civic and political involvement

Annual Hungarian Political Science Association Meeting, Cluj-Napoca, Romania 06/2013 When does information matter? Complexity, Cognitive Heuristics and Democratic Competence

Contested Claims on Citizenship in the CEE Post-Socialist Welfare States, CEU, Hungary 06/2012

Immaturity and Shortsightedness: Racialization and the Romanian Welfare State

PROGRAMMING AND LANGUAGE SKILLS

Software & Other Tools: R & RStudio, R Markdown & Sweave, LATEX, Python, SPSS, STATA;

Languages: Romanian – native; English – proficient; Italian – proficient;

French – elementary; Spanish – elementary;